Okay, בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is ח' chet and
we pick up at the bottom of ז' עמוד ב'. zayin amud
bet. We are now embedded in the classic סוגיא sugya here about
ברכת birchas what we would call שבע ברכות, sheva brachos, which is
called ברכת חתנים birchas chasanim in the גמרא gemara and the ברכת
אירוסין. birchas erusin. And what we had seen yesterday, first of all,
was the language of טעונה ברכה, teuna bracha, which is somehow like
the כלה kalla requires a ברכה, bracha, which suggests an idea that
then we saw brought in by רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosfos quoting
מסכת כלה, Maseches Kalla, which is כלה בלא ברכה אסורה לבעלה, kalla
blo bracha asura le'ba'ala, that somehow that the כלה kalla is forbidden
and the ברכה bracha makes her permissible. So it could be reframed
as a type of a ברכה bracha on
sex and sanctifying the act of sex, but the language very much
also focuses, there's a little bit of a focus on the woman
as sort of the object that's being made permissible.
And we also discussed the question in the גמרא gemara about whether
the whole source of a מנין minyan is from this פסוק pasuk
about Ruth and Boaz, which is the blessing of the union and
so on, and the blessing of the people to Ruth and Boaz,
or במקהלות ברכו ה' ממקור ישראל Bemakhelos barchu Hashem mi'mekor Yisrael and
the question of מקור mekor where it seems from the גמרא gemara
that that really has to do with sex and not with fertility.
So it clearly seems that this is a blessing of the people
that is given to the couple for their union and specifically with
the idea of sex as a piece of that and that's what
their union is about and in a way in which the ברכה
bracha sort of sanctifies that and therefore allows their sexual
act. מתיר, matir, again, whether technically it's אסור assur or not is
a different issue, but at least seen as a type of a
way of making that sanctified and permitted. So that in terms of
what we've seen so far about the שבע ברכות, sheva brachos, we're
going to see more, but now, and by the way, I should
mention that תוספות Tosfos also quotes a מסכת כלה Maseches Kalla which
mentions the ברכה bracha that Rivka's mother and brother gave her. And
that's the ברכה bracha not of a מנין, minyan, that's the ברכה
bracha of two people, but it's also ברכה bracha only to the
כלה, kalla, not to the couple. So there's a question if that
is really seen as a serious of a מקור. makor. תוספות Tosfos
also suggests maybe that's a מקור makor to ברכת אירוסין birchas erusin
although that also seems a little less relevant for that. So let's
take a look. Really what we've been seeing is ברכת נישואין birchas
nisuin about the couple, the union of the couple, related to sex,
related to making the sex permitted or sanctified.
Yes, and the ברכה, bracha, ברכה bracha was, was Rivka, Rivka was,
was
fertility
rather than sex.
אחותנו את היי לאלפי רבבה. Achoseinu at hayi l'alfei revava. That's a
good point too. Right, and also the idea of מנין minyan as
מנין minyan is definitely required for ברכת חתנים birchas chasanim because again
it is this ברכה bracha of the ציבור tzibur to the חתן
chasan and the כלה. kalla. So now, and the גמרא gemara had
the, and the גמרא gemara of course had the question here about
a case where you could even
have sex before the נישואין, nisuin,
which is the case of Yehuda after the אירוסין, erusin, and it
might be required there too, which is a little ironic because the
text of the ברכה bracha definitely seems to be about them starting
their married life and that would really focus in very specifically just
in terms of the sex itself. So now we pick up with
the issue about ברכת אירוסין birchas erusin because the גמרא gemara says
that ברכת אירוסין birchas erusin would be בבית אירוסין, be'beis erusin, but
this is the first we've ever heard of something called ברכת אירוסין.
birchas erusin. It's not in any משנה. mishna. So now the גמרא
gemara looks at this. So we pick up with the following.
תניא אידך. Tanya idach. מברכין ברכת חתנים בבית חתן וברכת אירוסין בבית
אירוסין. Mevarchin birchas chasanim be'beis chasan u'birchas erusin be'beis erusin. ברכת אירוסין,
Birchas erusin, מאי מברך? mai mevarech?
What's the
ברכה bracha for ברכת אירוסין? birchas erusin? So רבין בר רב אדא
ורבא בר רב אדא תרוייהו משמיה דרב יהודה אמרי: Rabin bar Rav
Adda ve'Rabba bar Rav Adda tarveihu mishmei de'Rav Yehuda amri: ברוך אתה
ה' אלוקינו מלך העולם אשר קדשנו במצוותיו וציוונו על העריות ואסר לנו
את הארוסות והתיר לנו את הנשואות.
Baruch atta Hashem Elokeinu melech ha'olam asher kideshanu be'mitzvosav ve'tzivanu
al
ha'arayos ve'assar lanu es ha'arusos ve'hitir lanu es ha'nesuos. Doesn't have the
word לנו, lanu, רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam added the word לנו, lanu,
just to clarify that the only נשואה nesua that a man is
allowed to have sex with is the one that's married to him,
על ידי חופה וקידושין. al yedei chupa ve'kiddushin. Okay, and then would
end it there. רב אחא בריה דרבא מסים בה משמיה דרב יהודה
ברוך אתה ה' מקדש ישראל, Rav Acha brei de'Rava misayem bah mishmei
de'Rav Yehuda Baruch atta Hashem mekadesh Yisrael, we have עמו ישראל, amo
Yisrael, על ידי חופה וקידושין. al yedei chupa ve'kiddushin. Okay, so we'll
unpack this language in a minute, but first let's just note of
course the idea that it emphasizes here of all things to say,
could have said אשר קדשנו במצוותיו וציוונו על הקידושין asher kideshanu be'mitzvosav
ve'tzivanu al ha'kiddushin or something like that or על האירוסין. al ha'erusin.
But the whole fact of אשר אסר לנו את הארוסות והתיר לנו
את הנשואות על ידי חופה וקידושין asher assar lanu es ha'arusos ve'hitir
lanu es ha'nesuos al yedei chupa ve'kiddushin again emphasizes again focusing on
sex and emphasizing that sort of like the idea that sex occurs
within marriage, that the idea of the קידושין kiddushin is sort of
the institution in which one's sexual life is supposed to take place.
Although again it does not say אסר לנו פנויות. assar lanu penuyos.
It says אסר לנו את הארוסות, assar lanu es ha'arusos, so that's
quite interesting right. there, right? It does seem to very much focus
on the idea of sex, but in an ironic way, not saying
that you don't have sex outside of marriage, but saying at this
stage of קידושין, Kiddushin, sex is still forbidden and it will become
permissible when we move on to the stage of the נישואין. Nissuin.
So in a very interesting way, it focuses on this as a
preparatory stage leading to, you know, ultimately נישואין, Nissuin, which is when
we will begin our married life. So it's quite a funny ברכה,
beracha, you know? It's about this whole institution מקדש ישראל על ידי
חופה וקידושין, Mekadesh Yisrael Al Yedei Chuppah VeKiddushin, you know, that this
somehow is an institution that sanctifies the people and that sanctifies, you
know, presumably the sexual life and the marriage and so on, but
still the idea of it operating in stages. And why that's underscored.
I'll just say one sentence about this, you know, it's maybe this
is more of a point to be made when we're learning מסכת
קידושין, Masechet Kiddushin, but the רמב"ם Rambam in the beginning of הלכות
אישות Hilchot Ishut says, you know, originally before מתן תורה, Matan Torah,
the marriage—and this is still the way it would be for a
non-Jew—marriage would be a man would see a woman and they want
to get married and they start living together and that would be
marriage. So it would be like poof, one act, an act of
marriage. Came along the Torah and the Torah was מחדש mechadesh that,
you know, it's two stages. First you have to do קידושין Kiddushin
and then afterwards there's נישואין Nissuin and you start living together. So
it sounds like from the רמב"ם Rambam there's this whole profound idea
that marriage exists in two stages, right? And why is that so
profound? Why is that a wonderful innovation of the Torah? What's the
value of it? Right, we could ask what is this idea? We
take it for granted: okay, there's קידושין Kiddushin and נישואין. Nissuin. What's
the point of making it two stages? So one thing that I
said I tell the, you know, the students is that at least
my פשט pshat about this is that, you know, if you just
start with the married life together then basically you only define the
nature of marriage by the reality of marriage, by the fact that
they're living together and have a happy married life and are having
sex with one another. It's defined by its reality. The reality, but
however in truth as we know, marriages go through tough patches and
there'll be times where the couple really is at odds with one
another and there's a lot of anger and frustration and they're not
having sex and all these types of things and you would not
say in any real world terms they're living as a married couple,
you know, that they have a real relationship and a married relationship.
But nevertheless, if the marriage were to break up at that moment,
right, then, you know, then you'd have a lot more broken marriages
than you have. I mean the idea of the marriage is that
there's supposed to be a contract and a commitment which doesn't mean
it can't be severed but which means that you're supposed to try
to get through the rough patches and see if you can, you
know, make it, you know, allow it to, you know, to persevere
throughout that period. And that is what I understand as the nature
of a קידושין, Kiddushin, a contract of marriage, a binding nature of
marriage that precedes the reality of marriage because there will be times
where the reality might not always be there and there will still
be, you know, this commitment to try to still work on the
marriage and to see it succeed. So I think that that's like
an important idea of having that sort of the, you know, that
binding nature of marriage that is not completely linked to the day-to-day
reality of them living together, you know, of them having a happy
marriage and living together as a married couple. Again, which doesn't mean
that that can't be severed, but it sort of points about like,
you know, about a sense of a commitment that transcends certain difficult
periods. So anyway, thinking about that in terms of this, you know,
that sort of speaks about these two stages. That there is—so this
is a ברכה beracha again ironically that's not that sex only occurs
in marriage, it's ironically a ברכה beracha that we don't have sex
yet. Actually it's אסור assur to have sex now after the קידושין
Kiddushin before the נישואין, Nissuin,
but and eventually though, you know, that that will be our full
married life later and that's why it even so it doubly relates
to the נישואין, Nissuin, you know, because then at the end, at
least with the חתימה, chasima, מקדש ישראל על ידי חופה וקידושין. Mekadesh
Yisrael Al Yedei Chuppah VeKiddushin. So in a way again it's a
funny ברכה beracha because it's pointing to the fact that, hey, this
is only a midpoint. ברוך השם, Baruch Hashem, this is only a
midpoint. We're not there yet, you know? So, but again so it
does maybe point to somehow the power of separating those two stages.
And again its focus on דווקא davka on sex, yes.
So then
as far as I understood it, this was the ברכה beracha they
made in יהודה Yehudah though because they were going to have sex
before.
No no no no no. This is the ברכה beracha we make.
No no. That the ברכה beracha they made in יהודה Yehudah was
ברכת חתנים. birchat chatanim. This is ברכת אירוסין, birchat erusin, yes.
So what was ברכת חתנים? birchat chatanim?
The שבע ברכות. Sheva Berachot.
Oh, but wasn't one of these one of them?
No. This is not שבע ברכות. Sheva Berachot. They don't make this—I
mean they make it under the חופה chuppah but that's what they
call ברכת אירוסין. birchat erusin. That's not שבע ברכות. Sheva Berachot. שבע
ברכות Sheva Berachot is what they do after the קריאת הכתובה. krias
hakesubah.
Okay. So the other
interesting—the other two points to make here is first of all על
ידי חופה וקידושין.
Al Yedei Chuppah
VeKiddushin. Everybody says why isn't it קידושין וחופה? Kiddushin VeChuppah? That's the
right order.
So one of the—so there's a Gaonic explanation that originally it was
a ב vet not a ו. vav. Because חופה, Chuppah, right, everybody
knows the word מהוי, mehavi, I forget what it is, אהוי, ahavi,
whatever, in the previous word. Anyway somehow the ב bet because it
comes after the ה hey from the previous word—I'm sure Dov here
could tell us what the rules are, I forgot, it goes back
about forty years when I learned this in day school—anyway the ב
bet loses its דגש. dagesh. So it's
על ידי חופה בקידושין. Al Yedei Chuppah BeKiddushin. It was בקידושין. BeKiddushin.
קידושין Kiddushin through—חופה Chuppah through קידושין. Kiddushin. That's a very ingenious read.
I don't
think—anyway—reading why don't— by קידושין וחופה. Kiddushin Ve-Chupa. So what the גאונים
Geonim say is it really is חופה בקידושין, Chupa Bi-Kiddushin,
חופה Chupa made possible through the act of קידושין, Kiddushin, but we
now have because we pronounce it וקידושין Vi-Kiddushin with a ב, Vet,
which now becomes confused with a ו. Vav. That’s a גאונית Geonic
interpretation of what’s that, oh it was a- interpretation oral, but yes,
eventually it got mistranscribed as a as a ו. Vav. But simply
that’s generally not understood, but what it means is again it points
to the fact that this is a ברכה Bracha that signifies that
this is only a middle stage. And by saying חופה Chupa first,
right, I mean it does a double thing. Number one it points
out to the fact that ultimately that’s the reality of marriage, right,
so we’re saying חופה Chupa first, you know, and the saying קידושין
Kiddushin last also at least allows us to end this ברכה Bracha
with the word of קידושין, Kiddushin, right, which is what’s happening now.
If we said על ידי קידושין וחופה Al Yedei Kiddushin Ve-Chupa we’d
be ending a ברכה Bracha of אירוסין Erusin with the word חופה.
Chupa. So I think it’s בדווקא, Bi-Davka, you know, done this way
to a say חופה Chupa is the where we’re getting, but קידושין
Kiddushin is what’s happening now. The other issue that comes up in
the גאונים Geonim is this language of מקדש ישראל על ידי חופה
וקידושין, Mekadesh Yisrael Al Yedei Chupa Ve-Kiddushin, where some of the גאונים
Geonim say אין קדושת ישראל תלוי בכך. Ein Kedushat Yisrael Talui Bekach.
What do you mean מקדש ישראל על ידי חופה וקידושין? Mekadesh Yisrael
Al Yedei Chupa Ve-Kiddushin? Like when do we say מקדש ישראל? Mekadesh
Yisrael? We say like generally אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו, Asher Kiddishanu Bi-Mitzvotav
Ve-Tzivanu, we say מקדש ישראל והזמנים, Mekadesh Yisrael Ve-Hazmanim,
but when do we ever say מקדש ישראל על ידי ציצית, Mekadesh
Yisrael Al Yedei Tzitzit, מקדש ישראל על ידי איקס, Mekadesh Yisrael Al
Yedei X, right? It’s like this is what קדושת ישראל Kedushat Yisrael
brings about, קדושת ישראל Kedushat Yisrael and I mean in the general
there might be מקדש ישראל שקדשנו במצותיו. Mekadesh Yisrael She-Kiddishanu Bi-Mitzvotav. So
some of the גאונים Geonim switch the גרסא Girsa and just say
ברוך אתה ה׳, Baruch Ata Hashem, I think it’s just מקדש ישראל.
Mekadesh Yisrael. They don’t have-
I’m trying to remember, they don’t have the על ידי. Al Yedei.
Argue so the על ידי Al Yedei and if we say that,
that’s then a really powerful statement if you stop and realize that
it’s the one ברכה Bracha that we say it’s this מצוה Mitzvah
that brings not generically מצוות, Mitzvot, but identifying not there’s no others,
but saying that this מצוה Mitzvah in particular is connected to קדושת
ישראל, Kedushat Yisrael, which has a very powerful idea of, you know,
of marriage and the family and that taking place in a type
of a קדושה Kedusha context. So there’s a power- a lot of
things to think about in terms of this נוסח הברכה. Nusach Ha-Bracha.
Okay, yes, you had a question.
Yeah, I understand that- that this is an innovation of the חכמים,
Chachamim, this ברכה, Bracha, but the language of אירוסין Erusin is already
in the תורה Torah itself like כי יארשה. Ki Ye-Arsah.
So there’s already implicit in the תורה Torah there’s not a sense
of the
stages.
Yes, רמב״ם Rambam would say the חכמים Chachamim innovated, said there’s a-
the תורה Torah innovated two stages, yeah.
Yeah, so- just
a quick comment.
But this is- harkens back to רש״י Rashi says, right, בכל מקום
שאתה מוצא ערוה אתה מוצא קדושה. Be-Khol Makom She-Ata Motzei Ervah Ata
Motzei Kedusha.
And since they’re not allowed to start living together, which is why
קידושין, Kiddushin, you know, קדושה Kedusha is also like a separating, you
have to separate yourself from your כלה Kallah and you still withhold
yourself and this is what’s also sanctifying you in other words.
And- yeah, yeah, yeah, okay, right, correct. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this, now what’s the issue of whether you make
a חתימה? Chasima? So whether you say this last ברכה Bracha ברוך
אתה ה׳ Baruch Ata Hashem at the end. So מאן דלא חתים
מדיהוי אברכת הפירות וברכת מצות. Man De-Lo Chasim Mi-De-Havei A-Birchas Ha-Peiros Ve-Birchas
Mitzvos. If you don’t make a חתימה, Chasima, it’s like when you
say בורא פרי, Borei Peri, when you say אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו
על נטילת לולב, Asher Kiddishanu Bi-Mitzvotav Ve-Tzivanu Al Netilat Lulav, you don’t
make a חתימה, Chasima, it’s just a ברוך אתה. Baruch Ata. ומאן
דחתים, U-Man De-Chasim, and if you make a חתימה, Chasima, מדיהוי אקידושא
Mi-De-Havei A-Kiddusha like by קידוש, Kiddush, you say right, you say אשר
קדשנו, Asher Kiddishanu, what is קידוש? Kiddush? אשר קדשנו במצותיו ורצה בנו
ושבת קדשו
באהבה וברצון הנחילנו,
Asher Kiddishanu Bi-Mitzvotav Ve-Ratzah Banu
Ve-Shabbat Kodsho
Be-Ahava U-Ve-Ratzon Hin-Chilanu,
blah blah blah, ברוך אתה ה׳ מקדש השבת. Baruch Ata Hashem Mekadesh
Ha-Shabbat.
So it’s a long ברכה Bracha and it ends with a חתימה.
Chasima. Now what’s the- what are these two versions about, whether you
compare it to ברכת הפירות, Birchas Ha-Peiros, ברכת המצוות Birchas Ha-Mitzvos or
קידוש. Kiddush. So תוספות Tosfos makes it completely a technical question. תוספות
Tosfos says, you know, ברכת המצוות Birchas Ha-Mitzvos and ברכת הפירות Birchas
Ha-Peiros is a short ברכה, Bracha, קידוש Kiddush is a long ברכה.
Bracha. So the basic answer is that when do you need to
sort of closure,
if it’s a long ברכה, Bracha, a whole paragraph, you need a
closure sentence. If it’s a short sentence, you don’t need a closure.
And this is middle sized, it’s longer than ברכת הפירות Birchas Ha-Peiros
and ברכת המצוות, Birchas Ha-Mitzvos, it’s shorter than קידוש, Kiddush, so that’s
a question, is it big enough to make a חתימה Chasima or
not? Okay, that was in- that was very boring, but that’s what
תוספות Tosfos says. Now the other- I mean it’s- it’s okay fine
it’s middle sized. רש״י Rashi starts by saying it really should be
in the short category. Why should it be in the short category?
Because it’s relatively short and he says as opposed to קידוש, Kiddush,
it doesn’t introduce new themes. One of the reasons קידוש Kiddush is
considered long is not just the number of words but the fact
that it introduces like it’s- it a little bit strays off topic,
it’s not just directly one idea. Here it’s only one idea so
technically it should be in the short category. So why should you
make a ברכה Bracha like קידוש? Kiddush? So רש״י Rashi says because
it has the word
of- of- רש״י Rashi says מדיהוי אקידושא, Mi-De-Havei A-Kiddusha, if you look
at רש״י Rashi ten lines from the bottom רש״י Rashi says כיון
דבלשון קדושה הוא כקידוש היום חתמינן ביה. Keivan De-Bilashon Kedusha Hu Ke-Kiddush
Ha-Yom Chasminan Beih. So since it has the language of קדושה, Kedusha,
right, על ידי חופה וקידושין, Al Yedei Chupa Ve-Kiddushin, it’s a type
of a קדושה Kedusha you’re gonna make a חתימה. Chasima. So that
actually says it has more to do with the nature of the
ברכה, Bracha, it’s not just like a גזירה שוה. Gzeirah Shava. And
this really opens up, right, this is such a beautiful three opinions
here in the גמרא, Gemara, because it really presents whether this was
the intent of the גמרא Gemara or not three different ways of
understanding what the function of ברכת אירוסין Birchas Erusin is. Let’s just
take It's a ברכת המצוה, Birkas Hamitzvah, that's the most obvious. You
make a ברכה beracha before a מצוה. mitzvah. You make ברכת אירוסין
Birkas Erusin אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו, asher kideshanu bemitzvotav vetzivanu, right? So
that sounds like a ברכת המצוה. Birkas Hamitzvah. That's one thing, on
the מצוה mitzvah of קידושין. kiddushin. That leads to a whole discussion
in the ראשונים, rishonim, is there actually a מצוה mitzvah of קידושין?
kiddushin? There's a מצוה mitzvah of פרו ורבו, peru urevu, is there
actually a מצוה mitzvah of קידושין? kiddushin? Major debate in the ראשונים.
rishonim. That's one approach. If the other if it's a מצוה mitzvah
by the way, right,
right, but exactly, but then you wouldn't call it a ברכת המצוה,
Birkas Hamitzvah, you might call it something else.
מדרבנן, midrabbanan, which are, okay, so
דאורייתא, d'oraisa, דרבנן, d'rabbanan, but are we framing it as a מצוה
mitzvah and calling this a ברכת המצוה? Birkas Hamitzvah? That's one approach.
That by the way leads to our practice which is that you
make it
before the מסירת טבעת, mesiras tabaas, like you make a ברכת המצוה
Birkas Hamitzvah before you do it. However, according to that, who should
be making the ברכה? beracha?
The חתן. chassan. Of course we're going to assume it's the חתן's
chassan ברכה, beracha, מצוה. mitzvah. There is a חתם סופר Chasam Sofer
that thinks maybe it's also the כלה's kallah מצוה, mitzvah, but the
general assumption always focuses on the man, so anyway certainly it should
not be the rabbi making the ברכה. beracha. That's, okay, so if
you do it before, we actually wind up doing a hybrid. We
make it before which assumes it's a ברכת המצוה, Birkas Hamitzvah, but
it's the rabbi making it which more reflects an idea of a
type of a ברכת השבח. Birkas Hashevach. We're doing this beautiful thing
called קידושין, kiddushin, we want to give praise to God for giving
us this wonderful institution of marriage, so it could be a type
of a ברכת השבח Birkas Hashevach which doesn't have to be made
by the חתן chassan himself, could be somebody who's just witnessing it
and so on. But we do an interesting hybrid because we have
the rabbi do it and we have it done beforehand. Now, there
are those ראשונים rishonim that say that it's done afterwards, that it's
a ברכת השבח Birkas Hashevach and it's not specifically the חתן chassan
and it's actually done afterwards. I was once at a wedding, and
it's a major מחלוקת ראשונים, machlokes rishonim, I was once at a
wedding where the the rabbi was a little bit unpracticed and he
they did the מסירת טבעת mesiras tabaas and he forgot to do
the ברכת אירוסין Birkas Erusin beforehand. So I said, so okay, go
ahead, do it afterwards, because there's enough ראשונים rishonim that say that
you can do the ברכת אירוסין Birkas Erusin after the מסירת טבעת
mesiras tabaas because it's actually a ברכת השבח. Birkas Hashevach.
So שבח shevach could be done before or after?
שבח shevach is always done after. You see the experience and then
you respond to it as opposed to ברכת המצוה, Birkas Hamitzvah, you're
making the ברכה beracha ahead of time to frame the act of
the מצוה. mitzvah. So those are two ways of understanding. Now, ברכת
הפירות Birkas Haperos and קידוש, kiddush, קידוש kiddush could be seen as
a type of a ברכת השבח, Birkas Hashevach, but קידוש kiddush is
also an important idea because קידוש kiddush says that this act, like
שבת, Shabbos, is sanctifying the day. And by making the קידוש kiddush
you're not only acknowledging that this is a sanctified thing and could
therefore be framed as a type of a ברכת השבח, Birkas Hashevach,
but it also is seen as you are actually also participating in
being מקדש mekadesh the day. By making קידוש, kiddush, it's not only
קדוש kadosh because God made שבת Shabbos holy, by you declaring it
as holy you're also adding that human element of you're sort of
adding a layer of holiness and sanctifying it as well. And that's
a different way of thinking about it, right? It's called קידושין, kiddushin,
it's we're sanctifying the union, you know, as it were, and that
the whole point of this ברכה beracha is about how this what
this sanctifies the sexual life and you know and the life of
the couple and so on. So by making the ברכה, beracha, it's
the you know the human recognition of that and the adding of
that layer of it. So that would be the קידוש kiddush dimension.
The ברכת הפירות Birkas Haperos goes back to what we discussed yesterday,
you know, that looks at it focuses it very much again on
sex as an act of pleasure and therefore how do you elevate
acts of pleasure, you know, in our you know you make a
ברכה beracha which sort of recognizes God that this is a gift
from God, you know, and this is so and therefore and sort
of by by framing it that way that sort of elevates the
act. And those three very nice different ways of looking at it,
and there's really a fourth way, which I said, which is just
purely שבח, shevach, although you could maybe tie that into the קידוש
kiddush idea. So there's a lot of different ways of conceptualizing it
with a lot of נפקא מינות. nafka minos. That is ברכת אירוסין.
Birkas Erusin. Now we're going to move back to ברכת חתנים. Birkas
Chassanim.
Yes? Very quickly, I mean, but if it's a ברכת המצוה Birkas
Hamitzvah then wouldn't it be phrased in the positive, like we say
על הטבילה? al hatevilah?
Right, so
that's why, because of this strange language, it pulls people away from
calling it a ברכת המצוה. Birkas Hamitzvah. On the other hand, the
reason that you have this is because they say it's not the
גמר מצוה, g'mar mitzvah, the גמר מצוה g'mar mitzvah is the חופה,
chuppah, so even if it's a ברכת המצוה Birkas Hamitzvah you need
to be framing it in the you know giving the full context,
don't think like this is it and you're done.
Right, she because it's קידושין kiddushin because
it has the language of קדושה, kedushah, therefore we frame it structure
it after קידוש kiddush and we make it have a חתימה. chasimah.
תנו רבנן Tano Rabbanan מברכין ברכת חתנים בעשרה כל שבעה. mevorchim birkas
chassanim be'asarah kol shiva. You say שבע ברכות, sheva berachos, I mean,
I'm okay, ברכת חתנים Birkas Chassanim as we're going to see שבע
ברכות sheva berachos comes later. Notice by the way ברכת אירוסין Birkas
Erusin it didn't have a בורא פרי הגפן. borei peri hagafen. You
make ברכת חתנים Birkas Chassanim the whole week. אמר רב יהודה והוא
שבאו פנים חדשות. Amar Rav Yehuda v'hu shebo panim chadashos. So that's
the whole week at the meals, okay, and רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
says that's when there are new guests that come because that increases
the שמחה. simcha. Says תוספות, Tosafos, just one short line in תוספות,
Tosafos, והוא שבאו פנים חדשות, v'hu shebo panim chadashos, אמר ר"י דפנים
חדשות אין קורא אלא בפני אדם שמרבין בשבילן השמחה יותר. amar Ri
de'panim chadashos ein koreh ella bifnei adam shemarbin bishvilan hasimcha yoseir.
People that add to the שמחה, simcha,
okay, otherwise and that's why somebody you're happy and adds to the
שמחה simcha because of their presence. Okay, and that's the whole idea,
if you already have this whole group and it's a continuation of
the שמחה simcha from the חופה, chuppah, the idea of these ברכות
berachos are an expression of joy, so is it a continuation of
what we've been doing or is it some new element of joy?
that allows for the ברכות Brachot to be made. Okay, so obviously
the idea here is that it's connected to the joy of the
wedding and the שמחה Simcha and to be able to make it
multiple times is that there's some new element of that.
מאי מברך? Mai mevarech? What is the ברכה? Bracha? אמר רב יהודה:
Amar Rav Yehuda: ברוך אתה ה' אלוהינו מלך העולם שהכל ברא לכבודו,
Baruch Ata Hashem Elokeinu Melech Ha'olam shehakol bara lichvodo, God created everything
for Your honor. We'll just read and then I'll say something about
it. ויוצר האדם, Veyotzer ha'adam, You've created the human. אשר יצר את
האדם בצלמו בצלם דמות תבניתו והתקין לו ממנו בנין עדי עד. ברוך
אתה ה' יוצר האדם, Asher yatzar et ha'adam betzalmo betzelem dmut tavnito
vehitkin lo mimenu binyan adei ad. Baruch Ata Hashem yotzer ha'adam, created
the human in His image and in and you know and fashioned
after after from him an everlasting structure, meaning an everlasting
meaning חוה Chava and you know the woman which was created from
the man and the עדי עד Adei ad might be indicating of
course the idea of like because then from there comes children and
leads to the you know human continuity.
So anyway the woman is created from man, blessed You God who
creates the human. שוש תשיש ותגל העקרה בקיבוץ בניה לתוכה בשמחה. Sos
tasis vetagel ha'akara bekibutz baneha letocha besimcha. Now we switch from the
couple to the more national aspect. The barren one, and again also
pointing towards the issue of fertility, but now you know the barren
one who would rejoice when her children gather in her, that's ירושלים.
Yerushalayim. ברוך אתה ה' משמח ציון בבניה. Baruch Ata Hashem mesameach Tzion
bivneha. So you know that's maybe an element but framing it in
the positive that even you know now that ירושלים על ראש שמחתנו,
Yerushalayim al rosh simchatenu, you know אם אשכחך Im eshkachech and so
on. So here it doesn't strike the sad note, it strikes the
happy note, but the happy note that indicates of course that ירושלים
Yerushalayim is not necessarily is not rebuilt, you know, and we're not
at the stage of pure שמחה, Simcha, but framing it in the
very positive, you know, this should be a model, this should ultimately
presage, you know, the returning of בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael of the
people to Israel, to ירושלים Yerushalayim and so on. So also you
know alluding to an aspect of fertility as well, which you know
is not always the case, you know, and again that's not made
explicit. So that's number so that's that.
שמח תשמח רעים האהובים, Sameach tesamach re'im ha'ahuvim, back to the couple.
כשמחך יצירך בגן עדן מקדם. Kesamechacha yetzircha beGan Eden mikedem. You know
you should rejoice. So it's not just that God created such a
thing as man and woman
but now there's actually the sense of they're now the man and
woman are coming together and they should rejoice like they did in
גן עדן מקדם, Gan Eden mikedem,
either עדן Eden in the east or עדן Eden from from you
know in the past. ברוך אתה ה' משמח חתן וכלה. Baruch Ata
Hashem mesameach chatan vechallah. Then ברוך אתה ה' אלוהינו מלך העולם אשר
ברא ששון ושמחה חתן וכלה גילה רנה דיצה וחדוה אהבה ואחוה שלום
ורעות. Baruch Ata Hashem Elokeinu Melech Ha'olam asher bara sasson vesimcha chatan
vechallah gilah rinah ditzah vechedvah ahavah ve'achvah shalom vere'ut. God created all
this types of rejoicing. מהרה ה' אלוהינו ישמע בערי יהודה ובחוצות ירושלים
קול ששון וקול שמחה קול חתן וקול כלה. Mehera Hashem Elokeinu yishama
be'arei Yehuda uvechutzot Yerushalayim kol sasson vekol simcha kol chatan vekol challah.
So this is interesting, right? It was a little bit bizarre that
we introduced the idea of ציון בבניה Tzion bivneha in between the
talking about the about creating man and woman and then bringing them
together and them rejoicing, right? That was like a little break. God
created man and woman, you rejoice ציון בבניה, Tzion bivneha, you rejoice
you know you bring together the חתן וכלה. Chatan vechallah. Like what?
But anyway but that's so it's a little chiastic, right? Because now
we bring those two themes together, right? So now we talk about
the God
creating all of this joy, and this joy ultimately will be the
ultimate joy at the time of redemption. קול מצהלות חתנים, Kol mitzahalot
chatanim, but and that joy at the time of redemption, you know
echoing the פסוקים Psukim in ירמיהו, Yirmiyahu, right, is there also a
joy of חתנים וכלות, Chatanim vechalot, you know, when they're you know
you know at their wedding day in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Of course it's
so powerful to make these ברכות Brachot in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. מחופתם ונערים
ממשתה נגינתם, Mechuputam unearim mimishte neginatam, ברוך אתה ה' משמח
חתן עם הכלה, Baruch Ata Hashem mesameach chatan im hachallah, the חתן
Chatan and the you rejoice the חתן וכלה. Chatan vechallah. So again
intertwining the joy of this couple, you know with the sort of
a sense of national joy. This is a not just the you
know and it makes it there's a lot of power to the
fact that this is made בעשרה Be'asarah and it's a blessing that
the community gives because part of what this is saying is this
is not just your private שמחה. Simcha. This is a שמחה Simcha
of the whole community. This is a שמחה Simcha that's intertwined with
a national שמחה, Simcha, you know, and so there's a real power
of bringing this you know having it sort of symbolic of and
framing it in terms of a type of a you know we're
all rejoicing with you and this all will be part of a
future national שמחה Simcha and giving it those much larger dimensions and
דווקא Davka ברכה Bracha made, you know, in a community amongst ten.
So those are the different elements. The difference between חתן וכלה Chatan
vechallah and חתן עם הכלה, Chatan im hachallah, רש''י Rashi says that
the חתן וכלה Chatan vechallah is not yet fully as a couple,
like the each one of that they should all be they should
both of them should have good you know they should have good
fortune, like you know they should be successful and you know רש''י
Rashi says בסיפוק מזונות וכל טוב, Besipuk mezonot vechol tuv, but the
last one חתן עם הכלה Chatan im hachallah means specifically they should
find joy with one another, not just that they should both you
know be A+ you know both of them are are living their
lives together and they're having a lot of success, you know, but
no they should actually find joy with within you know with one
another and the actual couplehood you know should be one of joy.
But it is funny though because the גן עדן מקדם, Gan Eden
mikedem, you know זאת הפעם עצם מעצמי ובשר מבשרי, Zot hapam etzem
me'atzami uvasar mibshari, you know that actually is about not just general
success but it's actually the joy of the coming together, the joy
of the union. So it's a little
But anyway, but allows us to make a different חתימה. chatimah. The
other question that comes up here is why some of these have
a ברוך Baruch and some of these do not.
The basic answer, I'll give you the answer that תוספות Tosafot gives,
תוספות Tosafot says שהכל ברא לכבודו Shehakol bara lichvodo and יוצר האדם
Yotzer ha'adam are short ברכות. brachot. And even though the general rule
is that when a ברכה bracha follows another one, it doesn't open
with a ברוך, Baruch, but if it's a short ברכה, bracha, then
it has to open with a ברוך Baruch or it'll just sound
like the same ברכה. bracha. If you said ברוך אתה השם אלקינו
מלך העולם שהכל ברא
לכבודו יוצר האדם, Baruch atah Hashem Elokeinu melech ha'olam shehakol bara lichvodo,
yotzer ha'adam, you would have just thought that that's like one ברכה,
bracha, a total weird ברכה, bracha, but it's one ברכה. bracha. Especially
realize that in the גמרא, Gemara, it's not like six different people
make the ברכה. bracha. So if you're just saying them straight and
you don't start the next one with ברוך אתה, Baruch atah, you
don't realize it's another ברכה. bracha. Similarly, if you didn't start אשר
יצר Asher yatzar with a ברוך אתה, Baruch atah, you'd take ברוך
אתה השם יוצר האדם אשר יצר את האדם בצלמו, Baruch atah Hashem
yotzer ha'adam asher yatzar et ha'adam b'tzalmo, it sounds like all one
ברכה. bracha. So you have to start those other ones with a
ברוך Baruch to separate them. Once you get the big one of
אשר יצר Asher yatzar and then you're going to introduce a new
theme with שוש תשיש, Sos tasis, that's obviously a different ברכה. bracha.
And that's why שוש תשיש Sos tasis doesn't open with a ברוך
אתה. Baruch atah.
And then אשר ברא, Asher bara, the last one, אשר ברא ששון
ושמחה חתן וכלה, Asher bara sason v'simcha chatan v'kallah, the reason that
starts with a ברוך אתה Baruch atah is because that's a ברכה
bracha that sometimes you make by itself. That's a ברכה bracha that
you can make, for example, we're going to see later, during the
week of שבע ברכות, Sheva Brachot, even if you don't have פנים
חדשות, panim chadashot, you would still make the, in other situations after
the, after the first week, etc., you might, well whatever, during the
first week, you might whoops make the ברכה bracha of אשר ברא
ששון ושמחה Asher bara sason v'simcha without the other ברכות. brachot. So
since it can occur as we'll find later without שבע Sheva without
פנים חדשות panim chadashot independently, it had to open with a ברוך
אתה. Baruch atah. So that's the intro, the technical question of why
some of them open with a ברוך אתה Baruch atah and some
of them do not. Another interesting point is that it comes up
in the פוסקים poskim that since you don't, for example, start שוש
תשיש Sos tasis with ברוך אתה Baruch atah because it's סמוך לחברתה,
samuch l'chavertah, if you give it to different people, would you have
to open it with a ברוך אתה? Baruch atah? Does that break
up the סמוך לחברתה samuch l'chavertah idea or if you accidentally said
it out of order or something like that? Anyway, רב משה פיינשטיין
Rav Moshe Feinstein says no. Once it was established with this נוסח,
nusach, it doesn't matter if you're dividing it among people or whatever
you're doing, you don't start things with, if they don't have a
ברוך אתה, Baruch atah, you don't start them with that. The last
thing I'll say about this is what's the ברכה bracha of שהכל
ברא לכבודו Shehakol bara lichvodo and יוצר האדם? Yotzer ha'adam? So רש"י
Rashi says that שהכל ברא לכבודו, Shehakol bara lichvodo, well יוצר האדם
Yotzer ha'adam is obvious. What's the ברכה bracha of שהכל ברא לכבודו?
Shehakol bara lichvodo? So רש"י Rashi interestingly says that that is actually
a ברכה bracha to the עם הנאספים. am hane'esafim. רש"י Rashi says,
where's רש"י? Rashi?
He
says, after the
period on the left hand side, like ten lines from
where it gets narrow,
there's a period on the left hand side where it says שהכל
ברא לכבודו. Shehakol bara lichvodo. Where are you? I have it right
here.
I don't have a period.
So what? Oh, okay.
אבל
שהכל ברא לכבודו, Aval shehakol bara lichvodo, thank you. אינה מן הסדר
אלא אסיפת העם הנאספים שם לגמול חסד זכר חסדי המקום שנהג עם
אדם הראשון שנעשו לו שושבינין ונתעסק בו ואסיפה זו מיהו כבוד המקום.
einah min haseder ela asifat ha'am hane'esafim sham ligmol chesed, zecher chasdei
haMakom she'nahag im Adam HaRishon shena'asu lo shoshvinin v'nit'asek
bo, v'asifah zo mihu k'vod haMakom. So רש"י Rashi says we're going
to see something like this by ברכת אבלים, Birkat Avelim, but this
is רש"י Rashi tries to introduce this theme here by the שבע
ברכות. Sheva Brachot. שהכל ברא לכבודו Shehakol bara lichvodo is all of
you that are gathered here today, right, what's, how do they say
that in the English ceremony? Dearly beloved, we are gathered here together.
Anyway, everybody who is gathered here today, right, to give, to be,
to rejoice with the חתן וכלה, chatan v'kallah, this is all כבוד
kavod of God because this is following in God's ways. You know,
God was משמח חתן וכלה mesameach chatan v'kallah as we're going to
see later, you know, and God is גומל חסדים gomel chasadim and
God is, you know, does all these things, and you to be
here and to give this joy to the חתן וכלה, chatan v'kallah,
this is all an honor to God because you're following in the
ways of God. So that's an interesting read of it. I don't
know if that's פשט. pshat. שהכל ברא לכבודו Shehakol bara lichvodo more
probably just points you to creation. God, everything God created was for
God's honor, you know, and God created the whole world and this
is all sort of recognizing obviously that this is all, you know,
from God and then to appreciate the unique creation of the human
being. But anyway, רש"י Rashi reads this specifically as a ברכה bracha
for the people. Okay, yeah.
How do we know this was דווקא davka by food? I mean,
where does it say that here?
So that's a very good question, right? There
conceptually there are two types of שבע ברכות. Sheva Brachot. There's the
one under the חופה chuppah and there's the one at the meals.
This גמרא, Gemara, although it speaks for the whole week, you know,
is not very clear at all that it's linked to the meals.
It's not very clear that it is, that there's a separate one
that relates under the חופה. chuppah. Part of this has to do
with looking at the תוספתא בברכות Tosefta b'Brachot which discusses this, which
does link it to the meals, and yeah, so it's not so
clear. What crystallizes later is those two categories, or not later, probably
it's there earlier but it's not made
clear. It does seem that they're very much two different types, one
that's linked to meals and that's the whole week, and one that
exists under the חופה, chupah, which is specifically linked to the נישואין,
nissuin, as I mentioned the other day. If you miss the ones
you're supposed to make during the meals, you don't make them again.
But if you never did the ones under the חופה, chupah, the
רמב"ם Rambam says you can make it even much later. Did I
tell you that case I paskened about the other day? No? Anyway,
it's a short version is that a couple got divorced and then
they basically started living together right afterwards and then they got 20
years later they decided they wanted to halachically get married again. So
the question is, you know, can you do another קידושין kiddushin or
not? Like maybe they were already remarried by the fact that they
started living together again. How do you consider that? Anyway, so I
told the rabbi, I said, well, I wouldn't make ברכת אירוסין birchas
erusin again, but you could do שבע ברכות, sheva brachos, because they
never did the שבע ברכות sheva brachos 20 years ago when they
started living together. So even much later you can still make that
שבע ברכות, sheva brachos, 20 years later. Anyway, fine. So moving on,
so those are that, but notice by the way there's only six,
right? The idea that a cup got added and בורא פרי הגפן,
borei pri hagafen, that comes at the Geonic period. Now as opposed
to ברכת אירוסין, birchas erusin, which everybody concedes is later and everybody
concedes is not really a part of ברכת אירוסין, birchas erusin, here,
the whole fact we call שבע ברכות sheva brachos here the בורא
פרי הגפן, borei pri hagafen, although not in the גמרא, Gemara, comes
in the גאונים Geonim is seen as much more intrinsic to the
שבע ברכות, sheva brachos, probably because as Michael pointed out, mostly שבע
ברכות sheva brachos occurs in the context of meals, and therefore that
probably is how the בורא פרי הגפן borei pri hagafen got seen
as much more part of it, but that's not in our גמרא.
Gemara. So let's take a look now back to our גמרא. Gemara.
Rabbi,
could you just say one thing? In the תוספות Tosafos it says
אשר ברא Asher Bara פותח ומברך poteach u'mevarech לפי שמברכים אותה בפני
עצמה lefi she'mevarchim osa bifnei atzmah כעין פנים חדשות. k'ein panim chadashot.
Yeah, I said that before, that you would say that if you
did not have a פנים חדשות panim chadashos and it's during the
first week, you don't say all of the שבע ברכות, sheva brachos,
but you still say the אשר ברא Asher Bara
and the גפן gafen I guess.
Yeah, right. Okay, so now let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. You don't say בורא פרי הגפן. borei pri hagafen. Okay, so
גמרא Gemara says like this.
לוי איקלע לבי רבי בהילולא דרב שמעון בריה. Levi ikla le'vei rebbi
behilula d'rav shimon breih. לוי Levi came to the house of רבי
Rebbi when it was the wedding party of רב שמעון, Rav Shimon,
רבי Rebbi's son. בריך
חמש. barich chamesh. He made five ברכות. brachos. So you see they
didn't divide it up but they apparently allowed a guest to make
the ברכות. brachos. רב אשי איקלע לבי רב אשי בהילולא דמר בריה.
Rav Ashi ikla le'vei Rav Ashi behilula d'Mar breih. רב אשי Rav
Ashi came to the house of רב אשי Rav Ashi when רב
אשי Rav Ashi was throwing a wedding party
for מר, Mar, his son, מר בר רב אשי. Mar bar Rav
Ashi. בריך שש. barich sheish. And he made six of the
ברכות. brachos. So
לימא בהא קמיפלגי. leima b'hai kamifligi. This must be the debate. דמר
סבר חדא יצירה הוי ומר סבר שתי יצירות הוי. de-mar savar chada
yetzira havai u-mar savar shtei yetziros havai. Do you is it two
ברכות, brachos, יוצר האדם Yotzer Ha'adam and אשר יצר את האדם בצלמו?
Asher Yatzar es Ha'adam Betzalmo? Because both of them are about יוצר
האדם. Yotzer Ha'adam. So what's the difference? Was it two or one?
Now what do you mean was it two or one? Obviously you
read the פסוקים. pesukim. It starts as one and then there's split
into two. Well, not really because depends if you're reading בראשית א
Bereishis Alef or בראשית ב, Bereishis Beis, right? Maybe did they start
as two or they start as one? Of course the גמרא, Gemara,
you know, isn't going to privilege one over the other. Obviously it's
not that they oh, it all started as two. Obviously it started
as one and they were divided. But the question seems to be
the way רש"י Rashi connects it to, was when they one of
the ways of reconciling those two stories is to say that the
first human that was created was half male, half female, like you
know front of side you know two halves stuck together back to
back. And therefore all along it was not as much a conceptual
second creation. It was really a dividing of what already was male
and female. So חדא יצירה הוי chada yetzira havai was it was
a dividing of already male and female as opposed to שתי יצירות
shtei yetziros which no first it was male, then it became male
and female. Is that clear? So if you see that as two
conceptually different stages you're going to make two ברכות. brachos. יוצר האדם
Yotzer Ha'adam which would basically be like the male, and then אשר
יצר את האדם בצלמו Asher Yatzar es Ha'adam Betzalmo בצלמו והתקין לו
ממנו betzalmo vehiskin lo mimenu and then you create a separate יצירה
yetzira of man and woman as opposed to just saying one ברכה
bracha which is the which is because it really always started as
man and woman and it was just being and they were just
being separated. So that's the question. Two ברכות brachos or one ברכה?
bracha?
So does that mean if you say just one then you make
the second one?
If you say presumably, yes. So the גמרא Gemara says לא. lo.
דכולי עלמא חדא יצירה הוי. de-kulei alma chada yetzira havai. Everybody would
agree that it was one. Okay?
Which according to רש"י Rashi means male and female stuck together. מר
סבר בתר מחשבה אזלינן ומר סבר בתר מעשה אזלינן. mar savar basar
machshava azlinan u-mar savar basar ma'aseh azlinan. But nevertheless the question is
do you go by what the plan was or do you go
by what actually happened? כי הא דרב יהודה. ki ha d'Rav Yehuda.
Like רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. רמי. rami. He showed a contradiction. It
says ויברא אלהים את האדם בצלמו בצלם אלהים ברא אתו. Vayivra Elokim
es Ha'adam Betzalmo, Betzelem Elokim bara oso. וכתיב זכר ונקבה בראם. U-ksiv
Zachar u'nekeiva bara am. Which was? Right? Was it originally male and
female or was it originally just, you know, male? So הא כיצד?
ha keitzad? בתחילה עלה במחשבה להיבראות שנים. bet'chila ala bemachshava l'hibaros shnayim.
Originally the plan was all along to have two. ולבסוף נברא אחד.
u-levasof nivra echad. But in the end it started as one and
it was divided as two. Okay,
so well... I mean I think that there's a power to this,
the whole idea, right, about, you know, emphasizing בראשית א Bereshit aleph
and the power about woman not just as an appendage of man,
but, you know, as obviously her, you know, an independent human being
and so on, equal in dignity and all of that and equal
creation of God. You know, but in the end creating one is
about the whole idea of couplehood, of the idea of being an
incomplete person and when you come together you become a whole. So
the power of the two stories together is extremely powerful about the
individual צלם אלקים tzelem elokim and dignity and then the power of
the couple. And if you read it that they were male and
female stuck together and it was not a male from which a
female was created, right, then that does not privilege the man at
all and it allows both for the idea of individual, you know,
sort of dignity and worth and at the same time the sense
of incompleteness and wholeness that comes when the two get together. So
there's a real power of both of those. How that exactly ties
in to this issue about it was חד יצירה chad yetzira and
עלה במחשבה ala b'machshava and whether it's one ברכה, bracha, two ברכות,
brachot, I'm always it always confuses me a little bit. I mean
I think that the point is that the end result was to
have two, so do you focus on the fact that okay, so
really it's like one thing because in the end it was just
how you got to the end result to separate, you know, to
create male and female, or do you say yeah, but it happened
in like two stages. And since it happened in two stages, you
know, we're going, you know, first there was created one and then
they were separated, we're going to make two ברכות. brachot.
Yes, there's really
the מחלוקת machloket as I understand it also has the following dimension.
For you to be a full or complete human being, you could
דרשן darshan that two ways. One is through the unity of two
becoming one. Yeah.
Or
through the separation so that you gain an autonomy. That is to
say the separation itself grounds a wholeness as it were. That's nice.
Right. Right, that's a very nice point, that there's a wholeness in
the separation as well. Absolutely. So the interesting important point about this
is that the conclusion that in the end it was it was
what do you call it, it was נו nu חד
יצירה הוה chad yetzira hava basically favors the read that they were
originally created as male and female together, which is a, you know,
better read for our contemporary sensibilities. Okay, so moving on, so the
גמרא Gemara says like
this, one minute, let me just take a look at, let me
just check one...
Right, okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay, and that's how we do, we make two ברכות brachot and
it's שתי יצירות הוה shtei yetzirot hava and but it also reflects
as we've been talking about, I mean חד יצירה הוה chad yetzira
hava in the sense of male and female it was always a
male-female combo, but also speaks about the importance of each of those
stages. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, אמר רב אשי
איקלע לבי רב כהנא. Amar Rav Ashi ikla l'bei Rav Kahana. Rav
Ashi came to the house of Rav Kahana. יומא קמא בריך כולהו.
Yoma kama barech kulhu. On the first day he made all of
the ברכות, brachot, all six of the שבע ברכות. Sheva Brachot. מכאן
ואילך, Mikan v'eilech, okay, or seven, אי איכא פנים חדשות בריך כולהו.
ei ika panim chadashot barech kulhu. This is what we said before,
with פנים חדשות panim chadashot you make it on the other days
after day one to make it a different type of a שמחה.
simcha. ואי לא, V'ei lo, but if not, אפושי שמחה בעלמא הוא,
afushei simcha b'alma hu, it's just more שמחה, simcha, but presumably like
more of the same, not necessarily a new שמחה, simcha, but more.
מברך שהשמחה במעונו, Mivarech shehasimcha bimono, you do say שהשמחה במעונו shehasimcha
bimono which we haven't mentioned yet, which is the ברכת הזימון, birkat
hazimmun, right, ברוך אלקינו שהשמחה במעונו ושאכלנו משלו. Baruch elokeinu shehasimcha bimono
v'she-achalnu mishelo. So now that's something that we're introducing is how you
open the ברכה. bracha. ואשר ברא V'asher bara ואשר ברא v'asher bara
and here's אשר ברא asher bara coming by itself. אשר ברא Asher
bara the last coming by itself when you don't have פנים חדשות
panim chadashot but you still have obviously it's the first week, continuation
of the שמחה. simcha. By the way, the fact that we're introducing
שהשמחה במעונו shehasimcha bimono and a ברכה bracha in the זימון, zimmun,
again makes all of this very much anchored in the meal, right.
So although the גמרא Gemara is not explicit about that, again all
you know and it is a תוספתא בברכות Tosefta b'Brachot and so
on, it's clear that all this is anchored in the meal. What's
less clear is the idea of the שבע ברכות Sheva Brachot under
the חופה chuppah independent of the meal, right. That is also a
separate concept and that's sort of less made explicit here. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara continues.
מכאן ואילך Mikan v'eilech after the first week. I skipped a line.
ואשר ברא. V'asher bara. משבעה ועד שלושים, Mishiva v'ad shloshim, from the
for the after the first week but until thirty days. And by
the way, notice the parallels with with אבילות, aveilut, right. You could
sort of say, no, these are general stages of moving away from
a powerful event, which could be true, you know, there's a week
out, there's a month out, but also there are clear parallels and
the parallels are going to continue, there's going to be a whole
discussion which we'll get to right now about ברכת חתנים birkat chatanim
and ברכת אבילים. birkat aveilim. So there is this powerful, you know,
this apparent parallels. Okay, so for all you the Freudians can come
talk about that. Okay, so מכאן ואילך mikan v'eilech אי
אמר ei amar משבעה ועד שלושים.
mishiva v'ad shloshim. Thank you. What'd you say? Woody Allen. Woody Allen.
משבעה ועד שלושים, Mishiva v'ad shloshim, it's what is it, it's Eros
and Thanatos, right. Okay, משבעה ועד שלושים בין אמרוהו מחמת הילולא בין
לא אמרוהו מחמת הילולא. mishiva v'ad shloshim bein amruhu machmat hilula bein
lo amruhu machmat hilula. Whether you say that we're having the meal
for the sake of the wedding or not, בין לא מחמת הילולא
*Bein lo machmat hilula* מברך שהשמחה במעונו *M'varech Shehasimcha B'mono*. So it
doesn't matter פנים חדשות panim chadashos. *Panim Chadashos* for the from שבעה
*Shiva* to שלושים *Shloshim* there's no אשר ברא *Asher Bara*, but there
is שהשמחה במעונו *Shehasimcha B'mono*. So after the first week, the most
you're doing is you're adding this שהשמחה במעונו *Shehasimcha B'mono* in the
זימון *Zimmun* for a whole month. Right, we don't do that. מכאן
ואילך *Mikan v'eilach* after the month, אי אמר להו מחמת הילולא *I
amar lehu machmat hilula* if you say yeah it's three months out
but we're doing this you know as a for the sake for
the for the new חתן וכלה *Chosson v'Kallah*. You know for people
who weren't able to be there at the wedding or whatever, then
מברך שהשמחה במעונו *m'varech shehasimcha b'mono*. If you explicitly label it as
relating to the wedding you do שהשמחה במעונו *shehasimcha b'mono* up to
a year. ואי לא לא *V'ei lo lo*, and if not, not.
Okay, but after the first week at most you'll do is add
שהשמחה במעונו *shehasimcha b'mono* in the זימון *zimmun*. We do not do
that. ועד אימת אמר להו מחמת הילולא *V'ad eimas amar lehu machmat
hilula* and if you say that it's related to the wedding until
when? Now what do you mean until when? We said for the
first year. Okay so it says
did it say for the first year? No it didn't. Oh you're
right it didn't. It just said afterwards. Okay, so it didn't say
after the first year. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says until when?
Right so that's what's got to say. אמר רב פפא משמיה דרבא
תריסר ירחי שתא *Amar Rav Papa mishmei d'Rava treisar yarchei shata* for
twelve months, right that's where it says, first year, like again אבילות
*aveilus*. ומעיקרא מאימת *U'meikara meimas* is it possible when would you start
saying it earlier if you can say it so far out? So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes maybe you can even say it in
anticipation as you're getting building up towards it, which is not obvious
at all because you might need the actual event to relate to.
But okay, but the גמרא *Gemara* thinks you can. So אמר רב
פפא מכדי רמו שערי באסינתא *Amar Rav Papa michdi ramu se'arei b'asinta*
when you start putting the barley in like the I don't know
in the pot or something there was a particular thing that they
would do for a סימן טוב *siman tov*. If you look at
רש״י *Rashi* four lines from the bottom, יש שורין שעורים בעריבת מים
*Yesh shorin se'orin b'arivas mayim* they would put barley in a trough
of water להתיו שיכרא לצורך חופה *lehatyo shichra l'tzorech chupa* to either
to make the beers. Oh that wasn't yet the סימן טוב *siman
tov*. Meaning when they started getting the food ready. Okay. ויש אומרים
לשם חתן וכלה זורעים שעורים בעציץ לומר פרו ורבו וצמחו כשעורים הללו
*V'yesh omrim l'shem chosson v'kallah zorim se'orin b'atzitz lomar p'ru u'rvu u'tzimchu
k'se'orin halalu*. That'd be like throwing rice or something, you know they'd
be planting the barley
from after the אירוסין *eirusin*
before the נישואין *nisu'in* as you're doing the build up for the
נישואין *nisu'in*. Okay but you're just adding this line in the זימון
*zimmun*, you're not adding a real ברוך אתה *Baruch Atah*. Okay. ומעיקרא
מאימת
*U'meikara meimas* oh we did that. איני והא דרב פפא איעסק ליה
לאבא מר בריה *Aini v'ha d'Rav Papa i'asak lei l'Abba Mar brei*
Rav Papa married off Abba Mar his son ובירך משעת אירוסין *u'veirach
mish'as eirusin* and he actually made it even from the time of
אירוסין *eirusin* presumably שהשמחה במעונו *shehasimcha b'mono*. We're not again talking about
שבע ברכות sheva brachos *Sheva Brachos*, just as שהשמחה במעונו *shehasimcha b'mono*
because he was already he was already rejoicing, he was already in
the mood of the wedding from the time of the אירוסין *eirusin*.
So and you know presumably they had an engagement party, right? It
was לשם חתן וכלה *l'shem chosson v'kallah*, it was well before the
wedding
and he was going to say שהשמחה במעונו *shehasimcha b'mono* at the
engagement party. So the גמרא *Gemara* said שאני רב פפא דהוה טריח
ליה *Shani Rav Papa d'hava tariach lei*. No, Rav Papa is different
because he was rich and people would take care of the actual
חופה *chuppah* beforehand so for him he like there was nothing there
was no obstacles going from the אירוסין *eirusin* to the נישואין *nisu'in*.
Like he knew all the details would be taken care of. I
don't know, just cause you know the details are taken care of
doesn't mean you're yet fully in that zone.
Others claim it means he was wealthy and had people working for
him. Yeah.
I thought it meant that he was involved. No. Others are טריח
ליה *tariach lei*. רבינא איעסק ליה לבריה בי רב חביבא *Ravina i'asak
lei l'vrie bei Rav Chaviva*. So רבינא *Ravina* married off his son
to the house of רב חביבא *Rav Chaviva*, meaning to a daughter
of רב חביבא *Rav Chaviva*, ובירך משעת אירוסין *u'veirach mish'as eirusin* and
he said שהשמחה במעונו *shehasimcha b'mono* also from time of אירוסין *eirusin*.
אמר קים לי בגוייהו דלא הדרי בהו *Amar kim li b'gavaihu d'la
hadri behu*. I know they won't retract, they won't back out. Right?
Because there's always the question, right? And also is יסב *yasik* meaning
אירוסין *eirusin* or does יסב *yasik* means engagement? Anyway he says he
knew that they would see it through and therefore again what it
indicates sort of like the people that work for him is that
once you are there's no perceived obstacles even if you're not yet
like in like a you know in the early period beforehand but
if there's no perceived obstacles then you're already in the mode of
שמחה simcha *simcha*. You did קידושין *kiddushin*, נישואין *nisu'in* coming up, you
don't perceive any obstacles, maybe it's a year out but you're already
in the mindset, the couple's engaged, you're in the mindset of שמחה
*simcha*, so you say שהשמחה במעונו *shehasimcha b'mono*. So that's what he
said. Of course here it did not work out that way. לבסוף
לא אסתייע מילתא והדרו בהו *Levasof lo istai'a milsa v'hadru behu*. In
the end it didn't work out and they and they did back
out. Again if there was already אירוסין *eirusin* they would have needed
a גט *get*. But anyway so it just goes to show don't
be overconfident about that, okay? But what it is showing you is
from the time of אירוסין *eirusin* if you're again think about for
us once there's an engagement and then you know everybody throws engagement
party etc. are you in that mode of שמחה *simcha* if there's
no you know if there's no perceived obstacles? רב תחליפא בר מערבא
איקלע לבבל *Rav Tachlifa bar Ma'arava ikla l'Bavel* Rav Tachlifa bar Ma'arava
came to Bavel, בריך שית אריכתא *berich sheis arichta*. He made six
the six ברכות *brachos* we call it the seven but remember there's
only six and he you know he lengthened them. He added a
lot of words like some of them are short, he made them
longer and this shows reflects a time when the ברכות *brachos* were
not you know when the liturgy was not so fixed although our
גמרא *Gemara* gave pretty much word for word. ולית הלכתא כוותיה *V'leit
hilchasa k'vasei*. We don't rule that way, we rule like the language
we had earlier. רב חביבא איקלע לבי הלולא *Rav Chaviva ikla l'vei
hilula*. רב חביבא *Rav Chaviva* came to a ברית מילה *Bris milah*.
ברוך שהשמחה במעונו *Baruch she-hasimcha bimono*. Again, not the actual ברוך אתה
*Baruch Atah*, just adding שהשמחה במעונו *she-hasimcha bimono* in the זימון *zimmun*,
right? Because we've seen you can do it before the נישואין *Nisuin*,
maybe you can do it at any type of like a סעודת
מצוה mitzvah *seudas mitzvah*, any time that there's some שמחת מצוה mitzvah
*simchas mitzvah*, you add שהשמחה במעונו *she-hasimcha bimono*. So he added at
the ברית מילה *Bris milah*. וליתא הלכתא כוותיה *V'leis hilchasa k'vosei*, we
don't rule that way, משום דטרידי *mishum d'tridi* because they're like distracted
but more like distracted a little bit like disturbed or whatever, distracted,
disturbed. It's not pure שמחה *simcha*, דאיתא צערא לינוקא *d'isu tza'ara l'yanuka*
because the baby is crying, the baby is, it's a painful experience
for the baby, so it's not appropriate to say שהשמחה במעונו *she-hasimcha
bimono*, which leads to the אשכנזי *Ashkenazi* מנהג *minhag* of not saying
שהחיינו *Shehecheyanu* at a ברית מילה *Bris milah*, although ספרדים *Sfaradim* do
say שהחיינו *Shehecheyanu* because the שהחיינו *Shehecheyanu* on the one hand is
something that's new, it's a new מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* and so on,
but on the other hand it also links to a reality of
שמחה *simcha*. So, and this maybe the גמרא *Gemara* is reflecting has
some more mixed feelings. אמר רב נחמן אמר רב *Amar Rav
Nachman Amar Rav*, חתנים מן המנין min haminyan. *chassanim
min haminyan*, we need ten, you include the חתן *chassan*. Okay, it
sounds like you don't include the כלה *kallah*. I mean, they, I
say that because you say well obviously if you know you're talking
about a מנין minyan. *minyan* you don't include the, you know, it's
men or whatever, but because it's not so clear like that this
is conceptualized as like a דברים שבקדושה *devarim she-bikdusha* that needs the
מנין minyan *minyan*, and if it's an idea of like a ציבור
*tzibur* giving a blessing to the חתן *chassan* and כלה *kallah*, you
know, then and so it is true on the one hand you
have the פסוק *pasuk* of בועז ועשרה זקנים *Boaz v'asara zekeinim*, but
you know, תוספות *Tosafos* quotes the פסוק *pasuk* of רבקה *Rivka* where
it's her mother, anyway, so there are, you know, there have been
some recently that have argued that maybe women could be part of
the ten. But anyway, the גמרא *Gemara*, so there, so you could
see that there's some somebody from ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* wrote an
article about that. Anyway, the גמרא *Gemara* only discusses whether the חתן
*chassan* can count to the מנין *minyan*. חתנים מן המנין *Chassanim min
haminyan*, but and so you can count the חתן *chassan* to the
מנין *minyan*, ואין אבלים aveilim מן המנין *v'ein aveilim min haminyan*, but
if an אבל avel *avel*, there's, we're going to find out there's
a ברכת אבלים birchas aveilim *birchas aveilim* which you also need ten
for, and there the אבל avel *avel* doesn't count. And there's an
obvious answer, because there are very different roles for the חתן *chassan*
and everybody else, for the אבל avel *avel* and everybody else. The
אבל avel? *avel* is the mourner and everybody else are the מנחמים
menachamim, *menachamim*, are the consolers, whereas at the wedding, sure, only one
guy's getting married, one gal, but everybody is part of the שמחה
*simcha*. So therefore the חתן *chassan* counts as the מנין *minyan* to
say there's a lot of people, there's a קהילה *kehillah* here, you
know, that's part of the שמחה *simcha*, you know, and it doesn't
have to be other than you, including you. But by the אבל
avel, *avel*, he's not part of the מנין *minyan*. Okay, מיתיבי *meisvei*,
I'll ask you on this. חתנים ואבלים מן המנין *Chassanim v'aveilim min
haminyan*, we have a ברייתא *Braisa* that says that even the אבל
*avel* counts as part of the מנין *minyan*. So גמרא *Gemara* says,
מתניתא קרמית לרב *matnisa karami l'Rav*? You're going to ask רב *Rav*
from a ברייתא *Braisa*? רב תנא ופליג *Rav tanna u-palig*, רב *Rav*
is allowed to argue on ברייתות *Braisas*, he's from the transition transitional
generation between תנאים *Tannaim* and אמוראים *Amoraim*, he's allowed to argue on
ברייתות *Braisas*. אתמר *Itmar*, so we have this question about whether רב
*Rav*'s statement that the אבל *avel* does not count to the מנין
*minyan*, we're now being introduced to the idea of ברכת אבלים birchas
aveilim *birchas aveilim*. It was taught, אמר רב יצחק אמר יוחנן *Amar
Rav Yitzchak Amar Yochanan*, חתנים מן המנין ואין אבלים aveilim, מן המנין
*chassanim min haminyan v'ein aveilim min haminyan*. Okay, same teaching as רב
*Rav*, that the חתנים *chassanim* count to the מנין *minyan* and not
the אבל *avel*. מיתיבי *Meisvei*, I'll ask on this. חתנים ואבלים מן
המנין *Chassanim v'aveilim min haminyan*. There we are again, but this is
now with רבי יוחנן *Rabi Yochanan*. Okay, חתנים *chassanim* and אבלים aveilim
*aveilim* are from the מנין *minyan* and maybe the גמרא *Gemara* doesn't
want to say רבי יוחנן תנא ופליג *Rabi Yochanan tanna u-palig* although
רבי יוחנן *Rabi Yochanan* was pretty much first generation, so it's a
similar type of a question but now we at least have a
different answer. כי תניא ההיא בברכת המזון *Ki tanya hahi b'birchas hamazon*,
כי אמר רבי יוחנן בשורה *ki amar Rabi Yochanan b'shurah*. No, when
we say that חתנים *chassanim* ואבלים *aveilim* count מן המנין *min haminyan*,
that's by ברכת המזון birchas hamazon, *birchas hamazon*, and here you have
it explicitly tied, there's some ברכת אבלים birchas aveilim *birchas aveilim* that
occurred at the ברכת המזון birchas hamazon *birchas hamazon* that you needed
ten for, and there we did not do that yet, we will
get to it, and there we do not do now, and there
אבלים aveilim? *aveilim* count. When רבי יוחנן *Rabi Yochanan* says the אבלים
aveilim, *aveilim* don't count, we're not talking about a ברכה bracha *bracha*
at the ברכת המזון *birchas hamazon*, we're talking about שורה *shurah*. What's
שורה *shurah*? When you return, when the אבלים *aveilim* return from the
graveside, you know, people make two lines and they give them and
they give and they give ניחומה *nichuma* and they say words of
ניחום *nichum*, and there he says you know that the people who
make up the שורה *shurah* obviously have to be distinct from the
אבל *avel*, so that's when they're לאו מן המנין *lav min haminyan*.
Okay, so that's what he says. And you need ten. ואלא הא
דאמר רב יצחק אמר רב *V'ella ha d'amar Rav Yitzchak Amar Rav*,
so that which רב יצחק *Rav Yitzchak* says אמר רבי יוחנן *Amar
Rabi Yochanan*, מברכים ברכת חתנים בעשרה וחתנים מן המנין *mevorchim birchas chassanim
b'asara v'chassanim min haminyan*, וברכת אבלים בעשרה ואין אבלים מן המנין *u'virchas
aveilim b'asara v'ein aveilim min haminyan*, but one minute, we have a
statement that you don't count the אבלים *aveilim* to the מנין *minyan*
for ברכת אבלים birchas aveilim *birchas aveilim*. Now we are, you said
that you don't count them for the שורה *shurah*, but the שורה
*shurah* is just saying words of ניחומה *nichuma*, המקום ינחם *hamakom yinachem*,
right? So we have again, we have the statement that you do
count אבלים *aveilim* for the מנין *minyan*, we're saying that's for a
ברכה bracha *bracha* you're going to do at ברכת המזון *birchas hamazon*.
You don't count אבלים *aveilim* for the מנין *minyan*, that's for the
שורה *shurah*. But then we have a statement that says you don't
count the אבלים *aveilim* for ברכת אבלים birchas aveilim, *birchas aveilim*. So
ברכת אבלים *birchas aveilim* is not the שורה *shurah*. So what is
this ברכת אבלים *birchas aveilim* that they also don't count for? So
the גמרא *Gemara* says, ברכה בשורה מי איכא *bracha b'shurah mi ika*?
There's no ברכה *bracha* in the
שורה *shurah*. אלא כי קאמר רבי יוחנן ברחבה *Ella ki ka'amar Rabi
Yochanan b'rachava*, when you feed them the meal, the first meal, you
know, we do this too, like they come home from the
בית קברות *beis kvaros* and that there's like a special... So that
meal they would do it like in the street. That first meal
that they would be fed in the street, that would be a
one where you would have the ברכת חתנים which is normally attached
to ברכת המזון, okay, and there though the אבלים would not count
as part of the מנין. So the way we're reconciling it is
like the normal ברכת אבלים that occurs in ברכת המזון you count
the אבלים, but the first one where again there's clearly distinct roles
of the person who just came back from the from the cemetery
and is the אבל and then the people there that are there
to console who are the מנחמים, menachamim. when you make that ברכה
associated with that eating and with that סעודה, seuda, the אבלים are
not מן המנין.
Okay, yes, why a מנין for for these אבלים? What is the
סברא? sevara?
Right,
but again I mean it's something about experiencing these losses not not
by yourself but in the context of community. Now you're right, you
could say okay but if there's not enough people there אדרבה aderaba
you should try to still do things, but you know we wanted
to in the end we wanted to sort of make this a
communal event by emphasizing the need of the community to be there,
but yeah. So all right, let's just read one more line. ואלא
הא דאמר רב יצחק אמר רבי יוחנן מברכין ברכת חתנים בעשרה כל
שבעה וחתנים מן המנין וברכת אבלים בעשרה כל שבעה ואין אבלים מן
המנין, ve'ela ha de'amar Rav Yitzchak amar Rabbi Yochanan mevarachin birchas chasanim
be'asara kol shiva vechasanim min haminyan uvirchas aveilim be'asara kol shiva ve'ein
aveilim min haminyan, that you for the whole week ברכת אבלים is
you do it and you don't count the אבלים, so ברכת רחבה
כל שבעה מי איכא? birchas rechava kol shiva mi ika? So this
ברכה that you make at the, you know sort of at the
meal when you're feeding them, the גמרא's assuming you know that was
only the first meal, that's not all the later meals. So the
גמרא says yes, משכחת לה בפנים חדשות, meshkachas la bepanim chadashos, you
have it in a case of פנים חדשות. panim chadashos So now
we also have an idea of פנים חדשות panim chadashos, for not
new שמחה but for new מנחמים. menachamim Okay, so there's this idea
and we'll pick up with this tomorrow that besides this idea of
רחבה, rechava, that when the you have this meal with the אבל
and the first meal and then any future meal in which you
would have new מנחמים menachamim. and פנים חדשות, panim chadashos, there would
be this special ברכת אבלים that would be made, which would be
part of the מצוה of ניחום אבלים nichum aveilim and we're going
to see what it is, the same way the שבע ברכות is
part of the מצוה שמחת חתן וכלה, simchas chassan vekallah, the ברכת
אבלים is an expression of the מצוה of ברכת אבלים, and it
would be made for the whole week but it would be made
only again when there would be פנים חדשות, panim chadashos okay? And
in that case אין אבלים מן המנין ein aveilim min haminyan because
there's clearly distinct roles between the אבל and the מנחמים. All right,
פנים חדשות panim chadashos for אבל?
Yep, פנים חדשות for אבל,
and then we're going to know
what's the.